Guide to the Maureen Howard papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Maureen Howard papers,
1962-2002.
Howard, Maureen, 1930-
4.17 linear ft. (10 oversized document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1452
5420020
Maureen Howard is an American writer, scholar, and literary critic. She is best known for her second novel, Bridgeport Bus (1962) and her award-winning autobiography, Facts of Life (1982). The collection includes drafts, correspondence, and publication material for nine novels published between 1962 and 2001, as well as correspondence, essays, teaching notes, and personal material written during this time period.
Biographical Note
Maureen Howard, born in Bridgeport, Connecticut, was the daughter of William Kearns, an Irish immigrant and county detective for Fairfield County. Howard's early novels (Bridgeport Bus, and Before My Time) draw extensively on the influence of her own Irish-Catholic upbringing, with Bridgeport featuring prominently in subsequent works.
Howard is best known for her novels Bridgeport Bus, Natural History, and A Lover's Almanac, as well as her critical introductions to Virginia Woolf and Edith Wharton. Her writing often describe individuals who are "out of place” often focusing on female characters divided between the obligations of home, career, and private life. Her work is frequently compared to Virginia Woolf and Henry James, both of whom she cites as influences. Howard was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1967; her 1978 memoir Facts of Life won the National Book Critics Circle award.
As a self-identified "gypsy teacher," Maureen Howard has held positions at Columbia, Yale, the New School for Social Research, Brooklyn College, and the University of California, Santa Barbara. In addition to her novels, Howard wrote an op-ed column "Her" in the New York Times (1979), as well as critical introductions for Virginia Woolf, Edith Wharton, and several collections of essays and women's fiction. She currently lives in New York City and teaches writing at Columbia University.
This collection focuses primarily on her novels, beginning with the 1962 Bridgeport Bus and ending with her 2001 collection Big as Life; it also includes a broad representation of journalism, essays, and teaching materials through this period.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of material for eight novels written between 1962 and 2002, as well as her autobiography and a short play ("Songs at Twilight") published in 1977. Included are publisher's correspondence, drafts, edited manuscripts, and research notes, as well as illustration and art material for some of the later novels. The majority of the revisions are Howard's own; her correspondence with her publisher appears to be limited to minor edits and proofreading.
A note on the drafts: The revisions included in this collection are often fragmented. Howard apparently reused her own papers, and frequently included handwritten material interspersed with typewritten copies or new drafts written on the back of (apparently abandoned) older versions. Where there is no other apparent order, the material has been left in the order in which it arrived.
The collection also includes an extensive selection of Howard's journalism and critical writing, personal correspondence, and research on Howard's activism and political work. Overall, the material is in excellent condition, with the exception of newspaper clippings and magazine articles, many of which are acidic and have been either separated or photocopied to preserve their integrity.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1965-2002
Series II: Novels, 1965-2002
Series III: Journalism, 1985-2001
Series IV: Personal Material, 1964-2001
Printed Material
Subjects
Cavell, Stanley.; Howard, Maureen.; McLaughlin, Anne.; Scott, Joanna.; American fiction--Women authors.; Novelists, American--20th century--Biography.
Access Restrictions
Collection has no restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
George Minkoff Purchase 2003
- Series I: Correspondence 1965-2002
  This series consists of correspondence from the mid-1960s through the 1990s, including a range of personal material, postcards, and correspondence from Howard's work as a literature teacher, as well as correspondence with novelists and publishers. Of particular interest is correspondence with Joanna Scott, William Pritchard, Anne McLaughlin, Richard Powers, and Matthew Stadler, which provides a rich view of Howard's literary contacts during this period. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1965-2002, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Authors
    - Bell, Millicent, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cavell, Stanley, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Demas-Bliss, Corinne, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fussell, Betty, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kirshenbaum, Binnie, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Longenbach, James, 1995-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Maddox, Brenda, 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - McLaughlin, Ann, 1985-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Messud, Claire, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Powers, Richard, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pritchard, William, 1980-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Scott, Anne, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Scott, Joanna, 1993-2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Stadler, Matthew, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stephens, Michael, 1987-2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Tiberghien, Susan, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Postcards, 1975-2002, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 20 to 23)
  - Publishing, 1983-2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Teaching, 1982-2002, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 25 to 28)
- Series II: Novels 1962-2002
  This series includes correspondence, drafts, research notes, and publication material for each of Howard's eight major novels produced during this period, as well as her autobiography and her 1977 play “Songs at Twilight.” The bulk of this series consists of draft material for Howard's three most recent works, Natural History (1992), A Lover's Almanac (1998), and the collection Big as Life (2001), excluding her most recent novel The Silver Screen (published in 2004). Unless otherwise noted, this material is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Bridgeport Bus
    - Drafts--Chapters 1-12--incomplete, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Drafts--General--incomplete l, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Journal, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript--incomplete, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Notes--Editorial--Corrections, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Publishing material, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Not a Word About Nightingales
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Facts of Life
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Draft -- “Sweet Memories,” undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Notebooks, undated (2) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Songs at Twilight
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Drafts, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 16 to 17)
    - Manuscript, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Publicity, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Scores, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Before My Time
    - Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Script--Adapted, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Grace Abounding
    - Correspondence, 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Draft--Full--Proofreading, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 26 to 27)
    - Drafts--General, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Galleys--Annotated, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Notes--Handwritten, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Notebooks, undated (5 in 2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 31 to 32)
    - Poem, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Publicity material, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Expensive Habits, 1985
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Drafts--General--incomplete, undated, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 2 to 8)
      - “Child’s Play,” undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - “Deadline,” undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - “Kill Fee,” undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - “Rough Cut,” undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - “Wonder Book,” undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Big as Life
    - Correspondence, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Drafts--General, undated, (3 Folders) (Folder 16 to 18)
      - “Children with Matches,” undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - “The Magdalene,” undated, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 20 to 21)
      - “Speed of Light,” undated, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Jacket--Design, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript--Full, undated, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 8)
    - Mechanicals--Art, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Notes--Handwritten, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Research, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Natural History
    - Correspondence, 1992-1998, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Correspondence--Art, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Drafts--General, 1989, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Drafts--General, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 6 to 8)
    - Drafts--General, undated, (8 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 8)
      - “Arcade,” undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - “Cover Set,” undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - “Double Entry,” undated, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 11 to 13)
      - “Lives of the Saints,” undated, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 14 to 16)
      - “Moving Pictures,” undated, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 17 to 19)
      - “The Music Man,” undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - “Natural History Part II,” undated, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 21 to 23)
      - “Sister Brown,” undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - “The Spinster’s Tale,” undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - “Statues,” undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Galleys--Annotated, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript--Full, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mechanicals--Art, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Notes--Handwritten, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Research, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Lover’s Almanac
    - Corrections, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Layout--Design, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript--Full, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Publicity, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Galleys and Drafts (Box 10)
- Series III: Journalism 1983-2001
  Reviews, essays, and draft material for Howard's uncollected criticism, including Howard's foreword for the 1990 reissue of Mrs. Dalloway and introductory material for Howard's 1977 collection Seven American Women Writers of the Twentieth Century. Of particular note are 14 handwritten notebooks including research for essays, interviews, and lecture material. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence, 1976-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7 to 8)
  - Essays--General 1979-2001, (8 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 9 to 16)
    - “Bachelor and the Baby,” 1994 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - “Fashion Plates,” undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - “You are There,” undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Essays--Corrections, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks, undated (14 in 6 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 5 to 10)
  - Notes--Handwritten, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Research, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Reviews, 1982-1998, (4 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 13 to 16)
- Series IV: Personal Material, 1964-2001
  This series contains correspondence, notes, and teaching material from Howard's time as a visitng professor at Columbia and Yale, as well as notes on various political causes that she supported during this period. Of particular interest are a set of handwritten journal entries, dated 1964, that provide insight to the beginning of her novelistic career. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence, 1977-2001, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Correspondence--Teaching, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Diary--Handwritten 1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks--Teaching, undated (2) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Personal--Ephemera, 1970-1992 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Poems, 1964-1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Plays, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Publicity, 1978-1992 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks--Teaching, undated (2) (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Research--Activism, 1997-1999, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 11 to 12)
- Series V: Printed Material
  - Journals and Published Books (Box 11)